A Guide to the Thomas Balch Library Advisory Commission Photographic Collection, 1993-
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library Advisory Commission Photographic Collection 1993-
Thomas Balch Library
VC RG08
.15 cu ft
The collection documents the annual Loudoun History Awards Ceremony. Not all years are represented.
Thomas Balch Library Advisory Commission, Town of Leesburg, Leesburg, VA
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research
Acquisition Information
Thomas Balch Library Advisory Commission, Town of Leesburg, Leesburg, VA
Alternative Form Available
digital, negatives for some items
Accruals
1993.007X, 1994.0003X, 1994.0004X, 1995.0040X, 1996.0008X, 1997.0006X, 1998.0010X, 1998.0011X, 1999.0007X, 2005.0248, 2006.0208X, 2007.0183, 2008.0176, 2010.0119, 2010.0336
Historical Information
Ordinance number 94-0-16, adopted May 24, 1994 by the Leesburg Town Council, established the Thomas Balch Library Advisory Commission to encourage citizen involvement in governance of Thomas Balch Library. The Commission's mandatmandatee includes includes long-range planning for the Library, and it serves in an advisory capacity to the Library Director with regard to oversight and guidance of Library operations, staffing, maintenance, capital improvements and funding, assistance in the preparation of tthe Library's annual budget, and promotion of the Library, including private fund raising and cooperation with Friends of the Thomas Balch Library, Inc. Commissioners liaise with their respective Councilmembers and with the Town Council regarding Thomas Balch Library.
The Commission, which meets monthly excepting August, is comprised of nine members. Seven citizen members, appointed by the Leesburg Town Council and selected because of their interest in the Library, serve four-year terms. AA Leesburg Town Councilmember and the Leesburg representative from the Loudoun County Board of Supervisors serve terms corresponding to their official tenures. A chairpersonOfficers are is elected annually by the members.
The Commission sponsors the annual Loudoun History Awards. The awards were established in 1993 to recognize contributions of local historian John Elbert Divine (1911-1996) in preserving Loudoun County history. The Loudoun History Awards highlight diverse aspects of the county's history. They honor individuals who have made significant contributions to preserving Loudoun's past through collection of county documents and memorabilia, preservation of historic landmarks, visual arts, writing and long-term involvement in local history organizations. Presented annually except in 2000 when renovation of Thomas Balch Library prevented the event, these awards have recognized some of Loudoun County's best known historians, writers, preservationists, and conservationists.
Balch Library Commission Members (reflects full or partial fiscal year membership; Board of Supervisors' terms reflect calendar year membership)
Atwell, George F. (Councilmanic 1995-1996, 2001-2002)
Bobich, Irene W. (2000)
Burk, Kelly (Councilmanic 2005-2006; Board of Supervisors 2007-2011)
Butler, Brenda (2007-2008)
Buttery, Jr., J. Frank (Councilmanic 1997-2000; 2002)
Clem, James (Board of Supervisors 2004-2007)
Dellinger, Donald (1998-2000)
Durand, Thomas H. (2004-2006)
Fera, Francis F. (2002-2005, 2007-)
Fishback, Mary (1995-2001)
Hall, Shirley McClain (2004-2007)
Hammler, Kathryn Sheldon (Councilmanic 2008, 2010)
Herring, Mark (Board of Supervisors 2000-2003)
Hershman, Jr., James (1995- )
Hiatt, Marty (1995-1999)
Hodge, Roger (2010)
Ingram, Mary E. (2002)
Kramer, Melinda (Councilmanic 2003-2004)
Lucier, James (1995-2004)
Marshall, Thomas C. (2003-2005)
Morgan, James A., III (2009-)
Paine, Leonor (2010-)
Roberts, James P. (2001- )
Rokus, Joan (Board of Supervisors 1994-1999; 2004, 2007-)
Schonberger, Martha (2003- )
Titus, Karen (1995-2002)
Tolbert, Jr., John (1995-2000)
Ward, Donald (1995-1996)
Watkins, Lou Etta (2005- )
Scope and Content
The collection primarily documents the annual Loudoun History Awards Ceremony. Images are individually catalogued in PastPerfect, Thomas Balch Library's visual collections database available onsite, and may be identified in the online index available at www.leesburgva.gov/ThomasBalchLibrary/SpecialCollections by searching vc_rg08. Photographs are not available for all years.
Loudoun History Awards Recipients
1993
John E. Divine
Louisa S. Hutchison
Carl McIntyre
Vinton Liddell Pickens
1994
Asa Moore Janney
Werner L. Janney
Charles Poland
Eugene Scheel
Frances Hazel Reid
1995
Ned Douglass
John G. Lewis
Frank Raflo
Bronwen Souders
1996
Richard Gillespie
W. Hugh Grubb, Jr.
Kathleen McCormick
Meredith Bean McMath
1997
Ruth and Willard Bishop
Esther Rogers Cowart
Agnes and B. Powell Harrison
Jane Norman
1998
Kim B. Holien
Ann Whitehead Thomas
Elaine E. Thompson
Landon O. Wynkoop
Loudoun County Historical Society members:
Joseph M. Rogers
Patricia R. Shoaf
Wm. Emory Plaster
1999
Tracy Gillespie
Joan Gillette Rokus
Wynne Saffer
Mary Alice Wertz
2000
No Awards Given
2001
Joni Crane
Mary Bettis Fishback
Deborah Lee
Dorothy K. Rickard
Loudoun Restoration and Preservation Society
2002
John Fishback
Olivia Marie Henry
Mattie Lassiter
William F. O'Keefe
2003
Evelyn Porterfield Johnson
Betty L. Morefield
2004
Peggy Sands Drummond
Carol Morris Dukes
Marty Hiatt
Rachel Yarnell Thompson
2005
Patricia B. Duncan
Betty Whiting Flemming
Thomas D. Horne
Pauline Singletary
2006
Allen Cochran
William H. Harrison
Lee Daniel Kent
Reginald Simms
2007
Laurel Brigade restoration and preservation group
Lou Etta Watkins
Cate Magennis Wyatt
2008
Mitch Diamond
Phil and Sandra Ehrenkranz
Stevan F. Meserve
James P. Roberts
2009
Anne Donovan Larson
W. Brown Morton, III
Henry G. Plaster
Mary E. Randolph
2010
H. Vernon Davis
Margaret T. Morton
Lori Kimball
Arlean Hill
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
An Ordinance establishing the Thomas Balch Library commission (12 April 1994), Town of Leesburg Ordinances, 94-0-16.
Thomas Balch Library Advisory Commission. Thomas Balch Library History Awards. Paeonian Springs, VA: Custom Graphics, Inc.: 2007.
Town of Leesburg. "Thomas Balch Library Advisory Commission." Town of Leesburg. http://www.leesburgva.gov/government/commissions/library/.
Other Finding Aid
Past Perfect Catalogue records
Technical Requirements
None
Related Material
TBL RG8 (Town of Leesburg - Thomas Balch Library Advisory Commission)
Contents List
- (Box 1)
  - 1993 Loudoun History Awards
  - 1994 Loudoun History Awards
  - 1995 Loudoun History Awards
  - 1996 Loudoun History Awards
  - 1997 Loudoun History Awards
  - 1998 Loudoun History Awards
  - 1999 Loudoun History Awards
  - Rededication May 19/20 2001
  - 2001 Loudoun History Awards
  - 2003 Loudoun History Awards
  - 2004 Loudoun History Awards
  - 2005 Loudoun History Awards
  - 2006 Loudoun History Awards
  - 2007 Loudoun History Awards
  - 2008 Loudoun History Awards
  - 2009 Loudoun History Awards
  - 2010 Loudoun History Awards